Jack: To improve skills and grow
professionally it is important
to get feedback especially on
how we communicate to others.
As we have already said, it helps us to
know that others understand what we are
communicating, enabling them to respond.
Leah: Feedback is a vital part of
any communication process and project
managers, team leaders, instructors
and coaches develop the skill of giving
feedback throughout their career.
They are also involved in receiving
feedback as well as this is an
important way of sharing information and
communicating within a work environment.
Jack: Feedback should be seen as
a positive thing as it can be used
to develop communication skills.
Feedback should be listened to
actively and analysed to help
improve future communications.
It can provide positive criticism and
allows everyone to improve their focus.
It can also create a healthy
communication flow up and down
the levels of an organisation.
Leah: Constructive feedback is
an excellent tool which can help
optimise the communication process
and increase transparency and trust.
Clear and honest communication flow
within a team, saves time and subsequently
money and can reduce errors caused
by miscommunication to a minimum.
Jack: By seeing that the feedback is
there to help projects succeed, it
can also motivate the team members.
Readily seeking feedback and ways to
improve, can help show the openness
to other ideas that may be beneficial.
It can also showcase unforeseen problems
and suggest alternative solutions.
Leah: But saying that feedback that is
negative or feedback that is not specific
can be unhelpful as it can demotivate.
The feedback should not just dismiss
the communication but should start
the process of engagement and debate.
Those giving feedback especially in a
work-based situation should themselves
become part of the problem-solving
process if the opportunity arises.
Jack: As we have previously discussed
listening is an important part of the
communication process and listening and
acting on feedback gives opportunities
for everyone to grow their skills.
Feedback is essential in communication
to know whether the recipient has
understood the message in the same terms
as intended by the sender and whether
he agrees to that message or not.
Leah: Feedback also enables us to evaluate
the effectiveness of our message and
if that feedback is timely then further
communications can be made to help
clarify any miscommunication or emissions.
Therefore, providing immediate
feedback enables people to better
learn from any mistakes they make.
However, if they communicate effectively
to begin with, it's still valuable
to provide feedback instantly, as
it reinforces that effectiveness and
motivates by affirming competence.